<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?xml-model href="http://www.tei-c.org/release/xml/tei/custom/schema/relaxng/tei_all.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<?xml-model href="http://www.tei-c.org/release/xml/tei/custom/schema/relaxng/tei_all.rng" type="application/xml"
	schematypens="http://purl.oclc.org/dsdl/schematron"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>Codebook bookcrit project</title>
            <author>Peter Boot</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <publicationStmt>
            <distributor>
               <name>GitHub</name>
               <ptr target="https://github.com/pboot/bookcrit"/>
            </distributor>
            <availability status="free">
               <licence target="https://www.gnu.org/licenses/gpl-3.0.en.html"></licence>
            </availability>
            
         </publicationStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <p>Born digital</p>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text>
      <body>
         <div>
            <head>Introduction</head>
            <p>This is the codebook for a pilot project researching the possibility of using a distant reading system for reading 
               Dutch online book reviews. The question that I am interested in is what issues are discussed in the reviews and 
               determine people's appreciation of the books that they discuss. The research is undertaken in the context of the database
               of Online Dutch Book Response (ODBR) discussed in Boot (<ref target="https://dh2017.adho.org/abstracts/208/208.pdf">2017</ref>). 
            </p>
            <p>The coding system is based on the system devised by Yvette Linders and described in her thesis <title>Met waardering gelezen</title> 
               (<ref target="https://repository.ubn.ru.nl//handle/2066/131544">2014</ref>). I modified and extended the system in several respects. See
               <ref target="https://pure.knaw.nl/portal/files/6529295/boot_adv_boekrespons.pdf">this powerpoint</ref> (in Dutch) for an idea of 
               what I'm trying to achieve. Mail <ref target="mailto:peter.boot@huygens.knaw.nl">me</ref> for more information.
            </p>
         </div>
         <div>
         <list n="aspect" type="codes">
            <head>Aspect</head>
            <item>
               <label>A</label>
               <term>Style/tone/language</term> 
               <gloss>Discussion of  tone and language use in the work,
               w.r.t. word choice, syntax and its connotations.</gloss>  
               <note type="samplewords">stijl, taal, toon, ondertoon, penvoering, zinnetjes, zinnen, toonzetting, woorden,
                  woordspelingen, woordenstroom, formuleringen, taalgebruik, vocabulaire,
                  verteltrant, schrijfwijze, taalbeheersing, woordkeus, schrijven, beschrijven, weergeven, vertellen, benoemen, formuleren, 
                  op papier zetten, noteren</note>
               <note type="usagenotes">vorm, vormvast: assigned by Linders to Structure, here seen as references to style </note>
               <note type="usagenotes">'Wieringa <mentioned>kan vertellen</mentioned>': J-A 15 (it isn't mentioned what is good about it, so keep it at 15)</note>
               <note type="usagenotes">'Wieringa <mentioned>kan verhalen vertellen</mentioned>': A-D 15 (applicable are J, A and D, choose A and D)</note>
            </item>
            <item>
               <label>B</label>
               <term>Structure</term>
               <gloss>Discussion of the macrostructure of the text, relations between the chapters
                  or other textual components of the text. </gloss>
               <note type="samplewords">structuur, orde, ordeloosheid, sprongen in ruimte
                  of tijd, vermenging, fragmentarisch, hoofdstukken, alinea's, lijnen, hoofdlijen, zijlijntjes, vooruitwijzingen, flash-backs, patronen, 
                  perspectiefwisselingen, 'rond' verhaal, compositie, vervlechten, in elkaar zetten, componeren, verknopen, onderbreken, verbinden, vermengen</note>
               <note type="usagenotes">lijnen, hoofdlijen, zijlijntjes: could be seen as Plot?</note>
               <note type="usagenotes">perspectief(wisselingen): is perspective part of Structure? It is often mentioned</note>
               <note type="usagenotes"><mentioned>verhaalmotief</mentioned> moved from G to here as it does not necessarily about topic</note>
            </item>
            <item>
               <label>C</label>
               <term>Setting</term>
               <gloss>Discussion of setting background of the story, in time, space, social background.</gloss>
               <note type="samplewords">ruimte, tijd, decor, milieu-tekening, schets van milieu, sfeer</note>
               <note type="usagenotes">Can also be indicated by names of specific settings: Amsterdam, the Sixties, high society, political circles</note>
            </item>
            <item>
               <label>D</label>
               <term>Plot</term>
               <gloss>Discussion of events and ending of the story</gloss>
               <note type="samplewords">plot, verhaal, verhaaldraad, slot, ontknoping, historie, handelingen, episoden, voorvallen</note>
               <note type="usagenotes">Can also be applied if say a specific episode is recounted</note>
               <note type="usagenotes"><mentioned>het idee van het boek</mentioned>: probaby usually refers to the plot</note>
               <note type="usagenotes"/>
            </item>
            <item>
               <label>E</label>
               <term>Dialogues</term>
               <gloss>Discusses how conversations between characters are represented</gloss>
               <note type="samplewords">dialoog, gesprek, woordenwisseling, uitspraak, vertellen, spreken</note>
               <note type="usagenotes"/>
            </item>
            <item>
               <label>F</label>
               <term>Characters</term>
               <gloss>Discussion of characters in the book</gloss>
               <note type="samplewords">personages, figuur, hoofdpersoon, karakter, mens, tegenspelerhoofdrol, bijrol, persoonlijkheid, sujet, held, type</note>
               <note type="usagenotes">Can also be used when characters are mentioned by name or profession etc.</note>
               <note type="usagenotes"><mentioned>Bildungsroman</mentioned>: F-G (theme is people)</note>
            </item>
            <item>
               <label>G</label>
               <term>Theme/idea</term>
               <gloss>Discussion about the topic that are written about.</gloss>
               <note type="samplewords">thema, idee, probleem, problematiek, gedachte, romanthese, visie, inzicht</note>
               <note type="usagenotes">Topic can also be mentioned by name rather than by category</note>
               <note type="usagenotes">Within the present coding systsem there is no way to indicate exactly what topic is being discussed</note>
            </item>
            <item>
               <label>H</label>
               <term>Symbolism</term>
               <gloss>Discussion of symbolism or metaphors in the work</gloss>
               <note type="samplewords">symbool, symbolisme, beeldspraak</note>
               <note type="usagenotes">Specifif symbols can also be mentioned</note>
               <note type="usagenotes"><mentioned>mooi beeld</mentioned> can refer to symbolism, but more usually is just refers 
               to a beautiful sketch</note>
            </item>
            <item>
               <label>I</label>
               <term>Appearance/presentation</term>
               <gloss>Discussion of paratextual and non-textual data, such as title, cover, publisher, genre indication, etc </gloss>
               <note type="samplewords">uitgever, titel, illustratie, afbeelding, foto, flaptekst, papier, verschijnen, presenteren</note>
               <note type="usagenotes">Genre indication: only code if the genre is thematized: <mentioned>for a thriller, it's pretty tame</mentioned></note>
               <note type="usagenotes"/>
            </item>
            <item>
               <label>J</label>
               <term>Author/ intention</term>
               <gloss>Discussion of author of the book and his/her poetics, intentions, person</gloss>
               <note type="samplewords">auteur, schrijver, schrijfester, intentie bedoeling, willen</note>
               <note type="usagenotes">Name of specific author is also an indication</note>
               <note type="usagenotes">Discussion about autobiographical aspects of book: J 8</note>
               <note type="usagenotes">If a review says that an author <mentioned>can write</mentioned>, that is not 
               necessarily just about style, and therefore: J 15 1 p (rather than J-A)</note>
            </item>
            <item>
               <label>K</label>
               <term>(Part of) entire work</term>
               <gloss>Discussion of the book as a whole or of parts of the book, where no reference is mode to specific aspects</gloss>
               <note type="samplewords">boek, werk, roman, verhaal, vertelling, deel, hoofdstuk, slot</note>
               <note type="usagenotes"><mentioned>verhaal</mentioned> is a difficult case, that will sometimes be just 
                  another word for the work as a whole, but in other cases may refer to the plot.</note>
            </item>
            <item>
               <label>L</label>
               <term>Other</term>
               <gloss>Discussion of other aspects</gloss>
               <note type="samplewords"/>
               <note type="usagenotes">Have not yet seen a case where this category was necessary</note>
            </item>
         </list>
         <list n="characteristic" type="codes">
            <head>Characteristic</head>
            <item>
               <label>1</label>
               <term>Efficiency</term>
               <gloss>Discussion of the efficiency with which the desired effects were obtained.</gloss>
               <note type="samplewords">efficient, zuinig, ter zake, details, uitvoering, (on)gecontroleerd, onopgesmukt, 
                  uitgesponnen, karig, lang, kort, langzaam</note>
               <note type="usagenotes">Includes negative remarks about volume of book: <mentioned>te dik</mentioned></note>
               <note type="usagenotes"><mentioned>traag</mentioned> used negatively (<mentioned>traag verhaal</mentioned>): D 1 -1 n</note>
               <note type="usagenotes"><mentioned>moet geduld hebben</mentioned> (negative): K 1 -1 n</note>
               <note type="usagenotes"><mentioned>met gemak geschreven</mentioned> I interpret easy of writing as written efficiently</note>
               <note type="usagenotes"><mentioned>geconcentreerde stijl</mentioned>: A 1 1 p</note>
            </item>
            <item>
               <label>2</label>
               <term>Coherence</term>
               <gloss>Discussion of the extent to which elements form a logical whole</gloss>
               <note type="samplewords">samenhang(end), combinatie, kloppen met, overeenkomen met</note>
               <note type="usagenotes">E.g. discussion whether a character and a plot turn are compatible.</note>
               <note type="usagenotes"><mentioned>geforceerde stijl</mentioned>: I interperet this as a style not fitting the subject or the 
               rest of the writing, i.e. as lack of coherence: A 4 -1 n</note>
            </item>
            <item>
               <label>3</label>
               <term>Continuity</term>
               <gloss>Discussion of continuity in a single aspect</gloss>
               <note type="samplewords">ontwikkeling, verandering, verschuiving, groei, afwisseling</note>
               <note type="usagenotes">May be applied e.g. (with end of scale -1) for characters that don't show any development.</note>
            </item>
            <item>
               <label>4</label>
               <term>Intensity/vividness</term>
               <gloss>Discyssion of whether a work is impressive or powerful, whether it contains energy or vitality</gloss>
               <note type="samplewords">Hevig, gematigd, zacht, vlammend, baldadig, sterk, bravoure, uitbundig, springlevend, 
                  speels, vaart, tam, mat verdorring, vitaal, levenloos, landerig, vlot, vlak, leven, flitsend, ongeremd</note>
               <note type="usagenotes"><mentioned>gekunstelde stijl</mentioned>: A 4 -1 n</note>
               <note type="usagenotes"><mentioned>vlot geschreven</mentioned>: A 4 1 p</note>
               <note type="usagenotes"><mentioned>levendig om te lezen</mentioned>, <mentioned>vlot te lezen</mentioned>, however: A 18</note>
               <note type="usagenotes"><mentioned>bizar</mentioned> is a difficult word. Can be used positively in this category, 
                  or negatively in category 8</note>
               <note type="usagenotes"><mentioned>pakkend</mentioned>: moved from 9 to 4</note>
               <note type="usagenotes"><mentioned>sensatie</mentioned> (in a negative sense): K 4 1 n (too lively)</note>
            </item>
            <item>
               <label>5</label>
               <term>Literary/intellectual characteristics</term>
               <gloss>Discussion of whether a work is literary, about the depth of a work, about its complexity 
                  or layeredness, about intellectualism and about whether it stimulates the intellect</gloss>
               <note type="samplewords">Literatuur, lectuur, diepgang, boeiend, briljant, intellectueel, geniaal, scherpzinnig, 
                  inzicht, zwaarwichtig, onbenullig, interessant, geraffineerd, triviaal</note>
               <note type="usagenotes">Removed <mentioned>fascinerend</mentioned> as it is certainly not only used for literary or serious work</note>
               <note type="usagenotes"><mentioned>intrigerend</mentioned>: even though suspense novels can also be called intriguing?</note>
               <note type="usagenotes"><mentioned>jongensboek</mentioned> as a reproach: K 5 -1 n</note>
               <note type="usagenotes"><mentioned>ernst</mentioned> was humour, but more suitable here</note>
               <note type="usagenotes"><mentioned>volwassen</mentioned>: might be used to indicate seriousness, but is also 
                  often used when an author of children's books has written a book for adults. </note>
               <note type="usagenotes"><mentioned>uitgewerkte personages</mentioned>: F 5 (though vividness and credibility might be considered too)</note>
               <note type="usagenotes"><mentioned>oppervlakkig personage</mentioned>: F 5 -1 n</note>
               <note type="usagenotes"><mentioned>iets te vertellen hebben</mentioned>: J 5 1 p</note>
               <note type="usagenotes">Use this characteristic for references to intertextuality</note>
            </item>
            <item>
               <label>6</label>
               <term>Humour</term>
               <gloss>Discussion of humour in the work</gloss>
               <note type="samplewords">Humor, satire, ironie, kolderiek, spot, spotziek, komisch, joligheid, meligheid, 
                  cabaret, vermakelijk, hilarisch, flauw</note>
               <note type="usagenotes">Linders here also includes what is amusing (<mentioned>vermakelijk</mentioned> or <mentioned>cheerful</mentioned>. 
                  I moved these to characteristics amusing (18) and upbeat (16).</note>
               <note type="usagenotes"><mentioned>irony</mentioned> and <mentioned>geestig</mentioned> are subtle humour: 6-20</note>
               <note type="usagenotes"><mentioned>glimlach</mentioned> is subtle humour : 6-20</note>
               <note type="usagenotes"/>
            </item>
            <item>
               <label>7</label>
               <term>Clarity</term>
               <gloss>Discussion of whether a work or aspect is clear, easily understandable, including of things that become clear immediately or only later in the work.</gloss>
               <note type="samplewords">toegankelijk, eenvoudig, makkelijk, moeilijk, helder, duidelijk, onverklaard, onontleed, uitdrukkelijk, nauw-verholen, suggestief, 
               cryptisch, geen hoogte kijgen van, verwarring, schimmig</note>
               <note type="usagenotes">Linders included <mentioned>spannend</mentioned>, which seems misleading.</note>
            </item>
            <item>
               <label>8</label>
               <term>Realism/credibility</term>
               <gloss>Discussion of agreement with reality or credibility</gloss>
               <note type="samplewords">realistisch, gelijkend, onwezenlijk, geloven, herkennen, (on)herkenbaar, levensecht, 
               overtuigend, ongeloofwaardig, onnatuurlijk, sprookjesachtig.</note>
               <note type="usagenotes"><mentioned>gekunstelde karakters</mentioned>: F 8 -1 n</note>
               <note type="usagenotes"><mentioned>filmisch</mentioned>: A 8</note>
               <note type="usagenotes">Linders includes here <mentioned>fantasie</mentioned>, and that is OK if it is meant to stress lack of realism. 
                  But for imagination I created a separate characteristic; it need not conflict with credibility.</note>
            </item>
            <item>
               <label>9</label>
               <term>Emotiveness</term>
               <gloss>Discussion of whether a work or an aspect of the work is emotional, expresses emotions, or evokes emotion</gloss>
               <note type="samplewords">snijdend, emotie, gevoel, gevoelig, voelen, verdriet, melancholie, ergernis, hartverwarmend, 
               ontroerend, aangrijpend, indringend, aandoenlijk, weemoedig</note>
               <note type="usagenotes"><mentioned>doet iets met me</mentioned></note>
               <note type="usagenotes"><mentioned>raak geschreven</mentioned>: A 8-9 (though efficiency, vividness and clarity would also be defensible, or even realism); 
                  compare <mentioned>treffend</mentioned>. 
                  In <mentioned>raak</mentioned>, I see as the essential element that the reader is surprised or hit by the fittingness of the description, in 
               <mentioned>treffend</mentioned> the element of fittingness is less important.</note>
               <note type="usagenotes"><mentioned>poëtisch</mentioned>: 5-9 (withouit further indications, probably A 5-9 1 p).</note>
               <note type="usagenotes"><mentioned>inspirerend</mentioned>: 9-13</note>
               <note type="usagenotes">An ending that is <mentioned>bevredigend</mentioned> is both emotionally acceptable and credible: D 8-9</note>
               <note type="usagenotes"><mentioned>sentiment</mentioned>: both emotion and not subtle: I code these separately, as 9 en 20 -1. 
                  <mentioned>niet sentimenteel</mentioned>: emotion and subtle, 9-20.</note>
            </item>
            <item>
               <label>10</label>
               <term>Didactic characteristics</term>
               <gloss>Discussion of whether a work or an aspect of it can teach the reader something, explain things or provide insight</gloss>
               <note type="samplewords">leren, uitleggen, ogen openen voor, begrijpen, aantonen, laten zien</note>
               <note type="usagenotes">Moral lessons belong to 13</note>
            </item>
            <item>
               <label>11</label>
               <term>Religious characteristics</term>
               <gloss>Discussion of whether a work or aspect of it is religious, has religious meaning, or whether religion plays 
               an important part in it. Other end of scale: atheism.</gloss>
               <note type="samplewords">stichtelijk, goed-christelijk, names of religions</note>
               <note type="usagenotes"/>
            </item>
            <item>
               <label>12</label>
               <term>Socio-political characteristics</term>
               <gloss>Discussion whether a work or an aspect of it is socially or politically meaningful. Antonym: apolitical. 
                  If the reviewer rejects the political views or objects to political content as such: code as 12 1 n</gloss>
               <note type="samplewords">maatschappij, samenleving, ideologie, geëngageerd</note>
               <note type="usagenotes"><mentioned>navelstaarderij</mentioned>: I interpret as a-social interest, 12 -1 n</note>
            </item>
            <item>
               <label>13</label>
               <term>Moral characteristics</term>
               <gloss>Discussion of whether the work expresses or discusses ethical norms or prevailing ideas of good and evil. Other end of scale: amoral. 
                  Immoral or objections to morality in general: code as 13 1 n</gloss>
               <note type="samplewords">(on)gevaarlijk, moraliserend, verontrustend, problematiek, probleem</note>
               <note type="usagenotes"><mentioned>een heroïsch verhaal</mentioned>: F 13 1 p; possibly, if there are overtones of admiration, F 9-13 1 p.
               <mentioned>held</mentioned>, if used in the general sense, is a moral characteristic F 13. If used in the sense of 
               'character', just code F (15?)</note>
               <note type="usagenotes">Also used when the question is raised how morally we would act in the described situation.</note>
               <note type="usagenotes"></note>
            </item>
            <item>
               <label>14</label>
               <term>Originality</term>
               <gloss>Discussion of whether the work or an aspect of it is new or original </gloss>
               <note type="samplewords">origineel, oorspronkelijk, eigenzinnig, onvervalst, nieuw, bekend, cliché, zoveelste, versleten, 
               creatief, afwijken, overeenkomen, variëren, imitatie, gemeenplaatsen, experimenteel, onnavolgbaar, persoonlijk, verrassend </note>
               <note type="usagenotes"><mentioned>maf</mentioned> in positive sense is original</note>
               <note type="usagenotes">Also original: <mentioned>vernieuwend</mentioned>, <mentioned>verfrissend</mentioned></note>
               <note type="usagenotes"><mentioned>allebehalve voorspelbaar</mentioned>: shows originality, but may be applied at multiple levels</note>
               <note type="usagenotes"><mentioned>klassiek verhaal</mentioned>: D 14 -1 p (positively appreciated lack of originality)</note>
            </item>
            <item>
               <label>15</label>
               <term>General/Other</term>
               <gloss>General evaluations where non of the other characteristics apply</gloss>
               <note type="samplewords">goed, slecht, voortreffelijk, knap, uitstekend, mooi, fantastisch</note>
               <note type="usagenotes">General cannot have a scale associated with it. 
                  If end of scale has nevertheless been coded, it will be ignored.</note>
               <note type="usagenotes">General judgment about book: <mentioned>good book</mentioned>, <mentioned>wonderful book</mentioned>: K 15 p</note>
               <note type="usagenotes">General judgment about writer, such as <mentioned>a very capable writer</mentioned>: J 15 p</note>
            </item>
            <item>
               <label>16</label>
               <term>Upbeat</term>
               <gloss>Discusson of whether a work is optimistic, upbeat or pessimistic and gloomy. Not in Linders</gloss>
               <note type="samplewords">Optimistisch, pessimistisch, zwart, inktzwart, nachtmerrie</note>
               <note type="usagenotes">Good example: <mentioned>donker boek</mentioned></note>
            </item>
            <item>
               <label>17</label>
               <term>Phantasy/Imagination</term>
               <gloss>Discussion of the extent to which to work or its aspect show imagination. Not in Linders</gloss>
               <note type="samplewords">(rijke) verbeelding(skracht), fantasie(vol)</note>
               <note type="usagenotes"/>
            </item>
            <item>
               <label>18</label>
               <term>Amusing</term>
               <gloss>Discussion whether the work is a joy to read. Antonym: boring. Not in Linders</gloss>
               <note type="samplewords">vervelend, saai, leuk, lekker</note>
               <note type="usagenotes"><mentioned>lekker leesboek</mentioned>, <mentioned>lekker om te lezen</mentioned>, 
                  <mentioned>heerlijk om te lezen</mentioned>, <mentioned>levendig om te lezen</mentioned>: K 18</note>
               <note type="usagenotes"><mentioned>Genoegen, kostelijk</mentioned>: moved from general/other to this category</note>
            </item>
            <item>
               <label>19</label>
               <term>Suspense</term>
               <gloss>Discussion of the suspenseful character of the work or an aspect, including the feeling of suspense in the reader. Not in Linders</gloss>
               <note type="samplewords">spannend, retespannend</note>
               <note type="usagenotes">I removed suspense from the general category of emotion. There are many works 
                  that are nor particularly emotional in any sense except for the feeling of suspense that they evoke 
                  in the reader. I seems more usefull to keep this code separate. </note>
            </item>
            <item>
               <label>20</label>
               <term>Subtle/subdued</term>
               <gloss>Discussion of the subtlety and refinement of the work. Not in Linders</gloss>
               <note type="samplewords">refined, hoogdravend, bombastisch</note>
               <note type="usagenotes"><mentioned>sober, ingehouden</mentioned>: moved from Efficient to Subtle</note>
               <note type="usagenotes"><mentioned>gezwollen, bombast, subtiel, ingetogen</mentioned>: moved from Intensity/vividness to Subtle</note>
               <note type="usagenotes"><mentioned>traag</mentioned> used positively (<mentioned>traaf en geduldig verteld verhaal</mentioned>): Subtle</note>
               <note type="usagenotes"><mentioned>moet geduld hebben</mentioned> (positively): K 20 1 p</note>
               <note type="usagenotes"><mentioned>zuiver</mentioned>: moved from religion to this category</note>
               <note type="usagenotes"><mentioned>elegant</mentioned>: included in this category</note>
            </item>
            <item>
               <label>21</label>
               <term>Identification/aborption</term>
               <gloss>discussion of whether the reader can identify with the book or some aspect of it. Not in Linders</gloss>
               <note type="samplewords">identificeren, invoelbaar, inleven, zich herkennen in</note>
               <note type="usagenotes">This was a category that Linders included in the pilot version of her system but removed from the final version. 
               She argues that in the small number of cases where it was used, the phenomenon might as well be coded as credibility or emotion. 
               Because of its importance in reading research I decided to maintain the category.</note>
               <note type="usagenotes">Category is also used to code <mentioned>pakte me</mentioned>
               <mentioned>meeslepend</mentioned>, <mentioned>meegevoerd</mentioned> etc. (though <mentioned>pakkend</mentioned> is merely intense)</note>
               <note type="usagenotes"><mentioned>het boek grijpt je</mentioned></note>
               <note type="usagenotes"/>
            </item>
            <note type="usagenotes"><mentioned>pff</mentioned> can mean many different things: sense of relief at end of boring book, heavily impressed by moving story. 
               Will only be coded if meaning is clear.</note>
         </list>
         <list n="end of scale" type="codes">
            <head>End of scale</head>
            <note type="default">0</note>
            <item>
               <label>1!</label>
               <term>Mentioned end of scale (overdoing)</term>
               <gloss>At mentioned end of scale but overdoing it. Originality e.g. is considered good, but work has too much of it</gloss>
               <note type="samplewords"/>
               <note type="usagenotes"/>
            </item>
            <item>
               <label>1</label>
               <term>Mentioned end of scale</term>
               <gloss>At mentioned end of scale: on e.g. the 'amusing'-scale, work is amusing, not boring.</gloss>
               <note type="samplewords"/>
               <note type="usagenotes"/>
            </item>
            <item>
               <label>0</label>
               <term>half-way/unclear</term>
               <gloss>Scale is mentioned but it is unclear at what end this work is, or it is somewhere in between.</gloss>
               <note type="samplewords"/>
               <note type="usagenotes"/>
            </item>
            <item>
               <label>-1</label>
               <term>Other end of scale</term>
               <gloss>At other end of scale: on e.g. the 'amusing'-scale, work is boring, not amusing.</gloss>
               <note type="samplewords"/>
               <note type="usagenotes"/>
            </item>
            <item>
               <label>-1!</label>
               <term>At other end of scale but overdoing it. e.g. <mentioned>too conservative</mentioned>: 14 -1! n</term>
               <gloss/>
               <note type="samplewords"/>
               <note type="usagenotes"/>
            </item>
            <note type="usagenotes">Not in Linders</note>
         </list>
         <list n="polarity" type="codes">
            <head>Polarity</head>
            <note type="default">u</note>
            <item>
               <label>p</label>
               <term>Positive</term>
               <gloss>Reveiewer apreciates the mentioned phenomenon</gloss>
               <note type="samplewords"/>
               <note type="usagenotes"><mentioned>aardig</mentioned>: usually the positive word in an otherwise negative environment. 
                  But interpretation depends on context.</note>
            </item>
            <item>
               <label>u</label>
               <term>Unspecified/neutral</term>
               <gloss>Reviewer expresses no (discernible) opinion about mentioned phenomenon</gloss>
               <note type="samplewords"/>
               <note type="usagenotes"/>
            </item>
            <item>
               <label>n</label>
               <term>Negative</term>
               <gloss>Reviewer dislikes the mentioned phenomenon</gloss>
               <note type="samplewords"/>
               <note type="usagenotes"/>
            </item>
            <note type="usagenotes">Not in Linders</note>
         </list>
         <list n="relation" type="codes">
            <head>Relation</head>
            <item>
               <label>r</label>
               <term>for a certain group of readers</term>
               <gloss>The opinion given represent how a certain group of readers might evaluate the book</gloss>
               <note type="samplewords"/>
               <note type="usagenotes"><mentioned>a story fit for schoolboys</mentioned>, <mentioned>for many people this will be moving</mentioned></note>
               <note type="usagenotes"><mentioned>jongensboek</mentioned>, if used as an observation</note>
            </item>
            <item>
               <label>w</label>
               <term>About other work of author</term>
               <gloss>The opinion given is about another work by the same author</gloss>
               <note type="samplewords"/>
               <note type="usagenotes"/>
            </item>
            <item>
               <label>g</label>
               <term>General</term>
               <gloss>The opinion given is a general opinion, not about this work. Not in Linders</gloss>
               <note type="samplewords"/>
               <note type="usagenotes"><mentioned>I dislike symbolism</mentioned>, <mentioned>suspense is what counts</mentioned></note>
            </item>
            <item>
               <label>t</label>
               <term>About other author</term>
               <gloss>The opinion given is about another author or his/her works</gloss>
               <note type="samplewords"/>
               <note type="usagenotes"><mentioned>Weg met de Gipharten</mentioned> (if used in discussion of a book by another author): K 15 -1 n t</note>
            </item>
            <item>
               <label>f</label>
               <term>Cites other person's opinion</term>
               <gloss>The opinion given is that of a teacher, friend, or other reviewer, not the reviewer's own. Not in Linders</gloss>
               <note type="samplewords"/>
               <note type="usagenotes">If opinion from other person (f) about other book (w): code as f. Example: 
                  <mentioned>De NRC-recensie over dit boek zei dat het qua thematiek tegenover Joe Speedboot staat</mentioned>: G 15 f. 
                  Can also be used for unspecified others <mentioned>after all the hype (I had expected more)</mentioned>: K 15 p f 
                  (p because the opinion of the other persons is positive).</note>
            </item>
         </list>
         </div>
         <div>
            <head>Issues with the coding system</head>
            <list>
               <item>Especially in longer reviews, all aspects tend to be discussed: plot and characters and style. 
                  So the coding might become very similar? But: in one review I might have 5 character aspects 
                  (in combination with different characteristics), in another one only one.</item>
               <item>Cannot make a distinction between very enthousiastic and moderately positive</item>
               <item>Do I need an aspect to take into account obervations, theories, thoughts, general statements 
                  included in a story?</item>
            </list>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
